<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Brief discourse of changing ministers tithes into stipends, or into another thing ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11104</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11683449</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11683449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 16:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Brief discourse of changing ministers tithes into stipends, or into another thing ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.G. for W. Lee ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. How tithes are of divine right, how not -- II. How canonicall, ecclesiasticall, politicall or judiciall -- III. How leviticall, how not -- IV. Not ceremoniall -- V. How alterable, and how not.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48137:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief DISCOURSE OF CHANGING MINISTERS TITHES INTO STIPENDS, OR, Into another <hi>THING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewed,
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>How</hi> TITHES <hi>are of Divine Right, how not.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>How Canonicall, Eccleſiaſticall, Politicall or Judiciall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>How Leviticall. How Not.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>Not Ceremoniall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. <hi>How alterable, and How Not.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. G.</hi> for <hi>W. Lee,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the ſign of the <hi>Turks-head</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Feter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane</hi> end, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:48137:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48137:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THeſe <hi>Quaeſtiones Spinoſae,</hi> perplexed and intricate Queſtions, whileſt that they have been by Canoniſts, School-men, and others curiouſly and learnedly diſputed, the Deciſion is left by them more dubious then they found them. Which gives occaſion to conceive, that there is a greater myſtery in ſearching out the Original Right of this ſacred Revenue, then ſome men of this Age do underſtand. Who therefore ought to be ſo much the more circumſpect, what they attempt herein, by how much the power of him with whom is the conteſt, is the greater: For the Diſpute is (not <hi>inter homines inter ſe Litigantes; ſed inter Deum &amp; Homines</hi> not betwixt men, but by men with God. <hi>Caſus tremendus, non temeritate exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendus;</hi> A Controverſie to be trembled at, not with temerity or raſhneſſe to be determined. For wo unto him that ſtriveth with his Maker. <hi>Eſay 45.9.</hi> Be wiſe now therefore, Oh you Rulers, and be Learned, yee who are Judges of the Earth.
<pb facs="tcp:48137:3"/>And in ſuch dubious and ſacred matters, be ſure to give judgement the ſafeſt way. For if your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be Erroneous, it is Robbery in the Superla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Degree.</p>
            <p>The laſt point hath onely been touched curſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by ſuch who have written on this Subject. And it never was ſo ſeaſonable here in <hi>England,</hi> as now, to be treated on purpoſely. Thou then who ſhalt be cenſorious of this Diſcourſe, let it provoke thee to pen a better, in the behalf of thy Mother the Church, which is the only ambition of him who thinks his name unworthy to be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for her Advocate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:48137:3"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe pretences for the Alteration</item>
               <item>Gods peculiar Reſervation of Tithes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</item>
               <item>God the Donor of Tithes to Prieſts and Miniſters.</item>
               <item>Gods Aſſignation to the Levites <hi>pro tempore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tithes Reverter to God after the Leviticall Law ended.</item>
               <item>Opinions of the <hi>Quo Jure</hi> of Tithes.</item>
               <item>The alteration, of great weight and concernment.</item>
               <item>The Inſtitution of the kinde, Morally and Natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Divine.</item>
               <item>Scrupulous conſciences ſifted and ſatisfied.</item>
               <item>Morally Divine or Judicials.</item>
               <item>Not Leviticall nor Ceremoniall.</item>
               <item>The end whereunto Tithes were ordained.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:48137:4"/>
               <item>Tithe not alwayes the Tenth.</item>
               <item>The end of their Inſtitution.</item>
               <item>How alterable.</item>
               <item>The pretence of contention anſwered.</item>
               <item>Whence the contention ariſeth.</item>
               <item>How the contention may with eaſe be prevented.</item>
               <item>Whence the ſtipend may iſſue, and its evill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences.</item>
               <item>The incertainty of Tithes examined and confuted.</item>
               <item>The alteration inconſiſtent with Law and Juſtice.</item>
               <item>Patronages deſtroyed by ſuch alteration.</item>
               <item>The now low, and to be lamented condition of the Church.</item>
               <item>A Caveat for Supreme Power, and its Bounds.</item>
               <item>The Sum, and cloſe of all.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48137:4"/>
            <head>A Briefe Diſcourſe concerning changing of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Tithes into Stipends or other Thing.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Miniſters, having been for many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges legally ſetled and eſtabliſhed in this Nation, and by Divine Providence having been both late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered from headlong deſtruction, threatned by a generation of men (ſhall I ſay) or rather beaſts in the ſhape of men: The Church cannot yet promiſe her ſelf ſecurity or ſafety; for though her enemies have bin prevented by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her level by a down-right blow, yet they will not ceaſe to ſolicite Supreme power to do their work by a circumference, and before the Church could be throughly ſenſible of her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid late delivery, they have already contrived how to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine her, by a ſpecious way held out of Peace and Profit, as it were, intended towards her. But if the Church muſt be deſtroyed, the difference is not great, whether it be done by the meanes of the open mouthed Ravenous Wolfes, or by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminings of the ſubtile Leering Foxes.</p>
            <p>Now in ſhort, the contrivance is, to take that from her which ſhe hath, and to find out a new way for her ſubſiſtance, and as is pretended leſſe ſubject to ſcruple and contention, and not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain. From which exchange, I ſhall pray for her delivery, and that Supreme Power will take the counſell of <hi>Solomon</hi> herein, <hi>Not to meddle with them that are given to ſuch change,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> 
               <hi>leſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ariſe ſudditinly on them both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of which Subject, the firſt thing to be taken into conſideration will be; By what Power and Authority Tithes became and were ordained, for the Miniſters Portion originally? Wherein ſome there are, and thoſe not a few, nor men of weak judgement and learning, that have held, written, and maintained that God himſelf was the firſt Donor of Tithes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48137:5"/>unto his Miniſters. And that though he be the Creator and Lord of all the World, &amp; gave the Earth, and the fruits thereof to the Children of men, that yet, in that very gift, he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in a peculiar manner, a Part or Portion thereof unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not that he needed any, but wherewith he would be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and have Religion perpetuated by the Sons of men, for their own good, who by their offerings of ſuch part of their goods, wherewith God did bleſſe them, they ſhould honour him with their ſubſtance as it is, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9. and acknowledge their Homage to him, and perform that ſervice towards him, which from the beginning was ordained them to do. And for proof of this truth, the offerings of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abell</hi> are alledged, who had no other commands that we read of, then the very dictat of nature herein to guide and direct them, And becauſe there was then no other Miniſtry ordained by God, therefore was this offering of theirs made unto God himſelf, which as ſome do conjecture, is for the part that which was afterwards called Tithes.<note place="margin">See Sir <hi>H. Sp:</hi> c. 24. p. 102.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For we do not read in Sacred Writ, that the Lord did own any other part for His, of the goods he had given unto man, (I mean Morally or Judicially, not Ceremonially) then Tithes, and of thoſe he ſaith, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30. that Tithes are the Lords, Holy to the Lord. As for other offerings, the Lord did never own them, till man had vowed or offered them. We ſpeak not of firſt Fruits or Sacrifices, or what was ceremoniall. But of Tithes, you ſee it is ſaid, that they are the Lords (not yet the Levites) in the Preſent Tenſe, and his peculiar Right, before they were either ſevered or paid, or aſſigned to the Levites.</p>
            <p>Now ſo ſoon as we read either of Prieſthood or Miniſtry. We ſee that God apointed that that part or portion of worldly goods, which by the Law of divine nature, man was to offer unto the Creator, was to be offered unto the Prieſt, for no man will doubt, but what <hi>Abraham</hi> offered or gave to <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> was by divine appointment, And that which he did give is named Tithes, but whether only of the ſpoiles as ſome would have it, or of all his ſubſtance as others affirm it, we will not here diſpute it. But what was this of <hi>Abrahams</hi> tithing for? Not for Sacrificing, for he offered nothing, but for bleſſing, which the Miniſters of Chriſt perpetually performing, the ſame
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48137:5"/>reward is due to them that did belong to the Prieſt, for no change of the Law, but by the change of the Prieſthood, which is the ſame of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> and Chriſt for ever.<note place="margin">Heb. 7.12.</note> And again that that which <hi>Jacob</hi> vowed was Tithes, not a voluntary vow as ſome would have it, but a dictat of divine nature, according to the example of <hi>Abraham</hi> his Grandfather, and in common underſtanding to be paid unto the Prieſt as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, the eldeſt Son of the Families being then the Prieſt, till <hi>Aaron:</hi> ſee more of this in Mr. <hi>Selden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The matter being thus ſtated and uncontroverted,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>S.</hi> p. 5.</note> that the great and wiſe Creator reſerved to himſelf a peculiar right in the Creatures (though the <hi>Quota</hi> be not agreed on) which he afterwards conferred upon, and aſſigned to his Prieſts in the dark times before the Law, it will under the Law be moſt plain and perſpicuous both for the kind, and for the <hi>Quota</hi> alſo, that the Portion which the Lord appointed to his Miniſters, the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> for their ſervice in the Tabernacle was (amongſt other things) of the Fruits and production of the Earth in kind, and the Tenth part thereof, truly called Tithes. For the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> being joyned to the Prieſthood the Houſe of <hi>Aaron,</hi> a Levite and his Sons, the Tithes by this were not taken from the Prieſthood, to whom they only belonged, but by that conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the Prieſts and Levites being united, Tithes became the Right of both as Prieſts; and the people paid their Tithes to the Levites, and they Tithes to the Prieſts,<note place="margin">Numb. 18.26.</note> but notwithſtanding this conjunction the Levites had only the charge of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle and <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons the charge of the Sanctuary, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and Veſſells thereunto belonging, and yet by reaſon of this union the Prieſts were ſometimes called Levites,<note place="margin">Ezech. 44.1 s. Heb. 7.5.</note> as in <hi>Ezech.</hi> 44. and the Levites Prieſts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. where it is ſaid that the Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> who receive the office of Prieſthood have command to take Tithes of the People. This obſervation will not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together uſeleſs, becauſe it meets with an objection that Tithes were taken from the Preſts, and given to the Levites, who were not Prieſts, and ſo became Leviticall, and ended with <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi.</hi> Whereas by this it appeares that the Levites were joyned to the Prieſts, and God might make whom Prieſts he pleaſed; and ſo Tithes were not take from the Prieſts, but belonged to the Levites, being joyned to the Pireſthood. Nor and Tithes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48137:6"/>been taken from the Prieſts by God, and given to the Levites, would that concluſion have followed, that Tithes muſt then end with the Levites, as ſhall be made more plain hereafter. Nor doth it follow, that, becauſe if God the Creator and true owner did take them from the one, and give them to the other <hi>Pro Tempore,</hi> therefore man may ſo do, or deſtroy them for ever, of which more hereafter.</p>
            <p>The firſt place in the Old Teſtament of the Law, where Tithes be ſpoken of expreſly, ſaving that of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> is that before remembred of <hi>Levit.</hi> the 27. 30. in which the Lord only declares his Right unto them. The next place is that of <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.21. where he aſſigneth them to <hi>Levi</hi> for an inheritance for their ſervice in the Tabernacle. Theſe two Texts of Sacred Writ, and the conſtant Practiſe of the Jewes in paying their Tithes during the time of the Law, even to the comming of Chriſt, as by that of our Saviour of Tithing mint, &amp;c. and by the boaſting Phariſees ſpeech to our Saviour of tithing all he poſſeſſed appeares, do ſo manifeſt the truth hereof, that it admits no diſpute, untill the Leviticall Law was abrogated.</p>
            <p>Now that Law ceaſing by the death of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt Jeſus; the next thing conſiderable will be, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of Tithes, when the Levites ſervice in the Temple ceaſed. For the Right underſtanding whereof, let us look a little back to that which hath been ſaid. For if it be true, which indeed cannot be denyed, that God did reſerve a Part and Portion of the Creatures as his peculiar Right, in the offering whereof, man for Gods bleſſing on his goods, was to expreſs his gratitude to his Creator and Benefactor, even by the Divine Law of Nature, which is ſo grounded in the Nature of mankinde, as that there never yet was any People, who honoured God, but held it their duty to do him honour with their goods; for it is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in Nature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hooker.</hi> P. 424.</note> a truth infallible, and an Axiome unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that men are eternally bound to honour God, with their ſubſtance from whom they have it in token of their gratitude. Nor ever was any people ſo barbarous, but did acknowledge a Deity, and to that Deity which they did ſo acknowledge, they naturally did offer of thoſe good things, which they ſuppoſed to receive from ſuch Deith. Upon which ground ariſeth that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48137:6"/>Interrogation of the Prophet, <hi>Will Any man ſpoil his gods?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.8.</note> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing the with holding of Tithes to be a violation of the Law of Nature, and not of the Levitical Ordinances. If this (I ſay) be a Truth, and that the part and portion thus due unto the Creator, be that which he calleth Tithes, (for other part of mans goods the Lord doth not challenge in that peculiar way, but Tithes he doth in expreſſe terms,) And them you ſee he beſtowes upon his Pireſts before the Law, and under the Law upon the Levites for their ſervice in the Tabernacle, (out of which ſtill the Prieſts had a Tithe) which aſſignation to the Levites, hath this tacite condition annexed unto it, that when that ſervice failed, then the wages ceaſed, and the Levites were no longer to enjoy their Tithes, then whileſt the ſervice laſted, for perofrmance whereof that wages was allowed, it follows of congruity, that thoſe Tithes part or portion which were the Lords peculiar right before the Levitical aſſignation, ſhould return again unto the Lord, as in his former right; for elſe we deny God that Reverter of his own proper and peculiar inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which we enjoy in ours, when the line faileth upon whom we make the Intail.</p>
            <p>And Tithes being thus reverted to God, not for any need he had of them, but for the need mankinde had of the Prieſts and Miniſters of the Goſpel. Which Miniſtery, as it ceaſeth not till the ſecond coming of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, ſo it cannot be ſupported without Temporal means, which leadeth us to the next Conſideration, Whether the Lord hath not aſſign'd that his right of Tithes unto the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Though it be true, that there is no ſuch expreſs Text of Scripture in the New Teſtament to prove the Lords aſſignment of Tithes unto the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as that of <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.21. to prove his aſſignation thereof unto the Levites, yet the conſequences and arguments drawn from ſeveral Texts of the New Teſtament, doe evidently enough prove Tithes to belong to them for their Miniſtery, as well as to the Levites for their ſervice.</p>
            <p>That the New Teſtament doth frequently command and call for a maintenance for the Miniſter, and that to be not onely competent, but honourable, we need not cite the particular
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48137:7"/>Texts of Scripture for it: That any other ordinary mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is intended the Miniſtery of the Goſpel, by the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, then Tithes, the Scripture is ſilent in it, and we muſt be ignorant of it. Nor doth it appear that the Lord hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe diſpoſed of this his Prieſtly patrimony: therefore we may with ſafety conclude, that the ordinary maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel intended by the New Teſtament, is partly Tithes, which if they may not enjoy, there is no other can claim or derive a title to. And the Maxime of the Law is, that <hi>In aequali Jure Melior eſt conditio Poſsidentis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The non-payment of Tithes to the Miniſters of the Goſpel in the Apoſtles days, and in the Primitive times of Chriſtianity, is no argument againſt their right; for till a Nation became Chriſtian, Tithes could not be paid, nor could the Miniſters of the Goſpel in thoſe times of perſecution, receive, collect, or retain them.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.12.15</note> The Apoſtle prevents this objection of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſage of their power, to be no prejudice to their right.</p>
            <p>It hath been, and yet is much controverted amongſt the Learned, by what right Tithes are due, ſome holding them to be due <hi>Jure Divino morali,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>S. P.</hi> 150.158.</note> as the Canoniſts generally, with whom agree many of our Engliſh and Learned Divines; but ſome agree the tenth part to bee only due by Law Poſitive and Eccleſiaſtick, and that there is no more <hi>Jus Naturale,</hi> or <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum Morale</hi> in it, then what commands a competence to the Prieſthood; and what now is, is in imitation onely of the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> ſtate ordered by the Almighty, and not obligatory under the Goſpel, but that the Church might freely have ordained a ninth, eleventh, or other part.</p>
            <p>Others there are who hold, that Tithes amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> were onely Judicials, and not due by Divine, Moral Law, or Law of Nature, but by the Civil Law of that Nation. And of this opinion are the Schoolmen generally, who when they ſpeak of their <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> they are to be underſtood to ſpeak of the Law Poſitive of the Church, imitating the Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicials, which retain their <hi>vim exemplarem,</hi> though not <hi>obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativam;</hi> neither do they make any difference betwixt Tithes praediall and perſonall, in this reſpect, which the Canoniſts do.</p>
            <p>Others there be, who hold them Ceremonial, and to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48137:7"/>with the Levitical Law, though they be not able to ſhew what the payment of Tithes did ſignifie, nor what they did ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifie, nor whereof they were a ceremony, which are the only Diſcoverers of that which is Ceremonial. In this varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of opinions, the queſtion amongſt the Canoniſts, School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Divines, not being yet determined by what Law Tithes are due (though it may be gathered for a truth, from the Scriptures, the Fathers, and other Humane Writers, that for ſo much as concerneth the due maintenance of the Miniſter, that it is due <hi>Jure Divino Morali,</hi>) by the Law of Nature, that yet the part as it was declared by the Judicial Law of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo is it due by the Civil or Poſitive Law of the Nation, but yet from the time of Grant or Dedication, to be the Lords to the worlds end, unleſſe himſelf, or perhaps the Miniſters his Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees, ſhall renounce or relinquiſh them.) It is no ſmall or trivial buſineſſe for thoſe in preſent power to go about an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal alteration of this ſacred patrimony. (Sacred, I ſay, that is, ſet apart towards the ſervice of God, in perpetuity under the limitation aboveſaid of the Lords or of his Miniſters renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation.) Before there be a judicious determination of its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal right, by an Aſſembly of Learned and Orthodox Divines, Lawyers, Canoniſts, and Caſuiſts, thereunto called by Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority.</p>
            <p>For if Tithes be due to the Miniſters of the Goſpel <hi>Jure Divino Morali,</hi> or by the Law of Nature in kinde, or in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, then will that State which ſhall alter them, or enforce an exchange of them for ſome other thing, be guilty of no leſſe ſin then Sacriledge, which is of ſo high a nature, that it coſt <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> dear; a preſident the higheſt of that nature, we read of, in the New Teſtament, intimating unto us, that ſin to be the greateſt which after the death of our Saviour was in all the Apoſtles times acted or committed. Not for breach of the Levitical Law, then ended; but of the Moral law, in withdrawing a thing devoted, the taking away what our forefathers devoted, (as Tithes) aggravates the offence, and ſo will do the puniſhment. Nor have thoſe parts or perſons wherein, or by whom it hath been practiſed, gone unattended with direful Judgements; Neither <hi>Germany, France, Holland,</hi> nor <hi>Scotland,</hi> (I will not ſpeak of <hi>Englands</hi> condition) can at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48137:8"/>this day glory of their proſperity, where that ſacred patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, with other of the like nature, have been ſwallowed up totally, or converted into Stipends or other things.</p>
            <p>And beſides the ſin of Sacriledge, it muſt needs be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a tranſcendent and high preſumption for man to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to be wiſer then his Creator. And whereas God in his wiſdome hath appointed Tithes to be the maintenance of his Miniſters, that man ſhould take upon him to chop and to change, to take away or confound what the Lord hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. When we pay our Tithes duly, we have in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſcharged our duties both to God, and to our Miniſter, either according to the Divine, Moral Law, or exemplary-wiſe by imitation of the Divine Judicial Law; but when Tithes ſhall be turned into Stipends, or ſome other thing now, or into <hi>Hoc aliquid nihil,</hi> hereafter, how can a man be ſatisfied when he hath paid or performed that, that he hath done what hee ought, or done his duty without diminution, the ſureſt way for God to have his right, and the trueſt way for man to do no wrong, is payment in kinde out of the very ſelf-ſame goods, which the Earth by his gracious bleſſing doth continually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. It was a witty obſervation of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that when a man pays his Tithes, he is the Husbandman, and receiveth nine parts for one, and God who receiveth one of ten is the Prieſt. But when Tithes are not paid, then God is the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, and keeps the nine parts, and man is the Prieſt, and hath but the tenth; for then ten acres of Vine ſhall yield but one Bathe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.10. So tender were the conſciences of men heretofore in point of Tithing, that few of them could be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied that they had ſo punctually paid them as they ought, and therefore uſually in their Wills they bequeathed ſomewhat to the Parſon for Tithes omitted, in lieu whereof the Mortuary is paid to this day: how ſeared are the conſciences of men now, that would pay no Tithe at all?</p>
            <p>Now thoſe who write againſt the Divine Moral Right of the <hi>Quota,</hi> or tenth part, yet ſtill agree that a part or portion of the Increaſe of the fruits of the Earth, &amp;c. in kinde, is the right of the Miniſters of the Goſpel by the Divine Moral Law, and by the Evangelical Texts of Muzling the Ox, Planting a Vineyard, Feeding a flock, and not partaking of the milk and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48137:8"/>Fruit thereof in kind, with many other places of the New Teſtament, which the Apoſtle urgeth not, as an Ordinance <hi>de Novo,</hi> but from the Law which proves moſt fully, that the manner of tithing under the Goſpell, ought to be as it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, both in kind and quantity. How then can it ſtand with the Conſciences of them in Power to alter the way, that God hath appointed for maintenance of his Miniſters? will they ſtill be wiſer then he?</p>
            <p>If the Tenth part be looked upon by the Repining people, as too great a Portion for Gods Miniſters of the Goſpell to enjoy, wherein thou man doeſt ſtill take upon thee, to be wiſer then thy Creator, who appointed his Prieſts that and much more among the Jewes. Why then doeſt not thou only content thy ſelf with an Abridgement of the <hi>Quota</hi> or part? but thou muſt be altering of the very Nature and kind alſo of that mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that God in his wiſdom hath by Divine Morall Law or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for his Miniſters, and not without viſible and pregnant Reaſon. For this way of maintenance, is ſutable to all times, both of plenty and ſcarcity; agreeable to all prices of Corn, Grain, Hay, and other commodities, the Prices whereof though they change daily, yet Nature being uſually the ſame, keeps the true ſtandard betwixt God and man. Again of conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency to all perſons both Pariſhioners and Miniſters, the one to go no further to pay, nor the other to recive whats due, then to the Land it ſelf within the Pariſh. And of beſt Equality, the Poor not burthened, nor the Rich eaſed, (for the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betwixt Tithe of Paſture and arrable, makes not Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unequall, comparing Land of the ſame quality one with another, but the inequality thereof proceeds from the owners uſage, who is at liberty to husband his Land, in what kind he pleaſeth, whether he be rich or Poor.) The duty more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed in paying Tithe in kinde, then by paying the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue thereof in money, which with moſt Farmors is uſually wanting, when their commodities are moſt plentifull, and may be better ſpared.</p>
            <p>And again it is more Naturall that Tithes be paid in kind then otherwiſe, For Tithes procure an increaſe of the Heap, out of which they are taken, and by the Jewes were accounted the very Mound, Fence, and Bulwark of all their ſubſtance. And
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48137:9"/>if you look upon the quantity,<note place="margin">See much more of this Number in Sr. <hi>H. Sp.</hi> c. 14. <hi>De Orb: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia. Lib.</hi> 3. c. 10.</note> Ten is the number of Natures perfection, beyond which we cannot go without iteration and Repetition. And <hi>Poſtellus</hi> telleth us, that it ſtands with Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that foraſmuch as all Creatures do bear the Character of Divine Power, Wiſdom, and Mercy of the Creator, That Tithes as well as Tribute ſhould be paid of, that to him whoſe Image and Superſcription they bear, How elſe do we give Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to whom Honour belongeth, or to God the things that are Gods, our Wealth being Gods, as well as the time of our Lives, whereof he Reſerved a ſeventh part to himſelf, but of the other only a tenth.</p>
            <p>And again Nature and Reaſon do plead for the Miniſter to participate with the People in that kind, wherein there may be equallity of fortune, and whereby Sympathy and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that great Bond of Nature, between the Church and Commonwealth is preſerved (as a late Learned Biſhop of this Church hath it) as in fair and ſeaſonable weather,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews.</hi>
               </note> and in times of Plenty, the Miniſter to rejoyce and praiſe God with the People, in want and tempeſtuous weather, to mourn and pray together, But where the Prieſt is a ſtipendary, when the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple rejoyce for Plenty, or lament for want, the Miniſter doth neither; for what is their Sowing, Mowing, or Reaping unto him, when the Bond of Nature is diſſolved, the like may be ſaid, where the Miniſter walketh, waiteth and attendeth for his (it may be two narrow) ſtipend that is withheld from him, for want whereof he, his Wife, Children, and Family Mourn, Lament, an Famiſh, what is all this to the People? there is no Sympathiſing one with another, either in Mirth, or Miſery, for the greateſt Bond of Nature is diſſolved.</p>
            <p>Let us now come to conſider of the Grounds, and Motives held forth for the alteration of Tithes, the ſetled Revenue, and undeniable Right, and Property of the Miniſters of the Church and the converting of them into ſtipends, or ſome other thing,</p>
            <p>The firſt Argument I find is, that the Payment of Tithes is ſcrupulous to tender Conſciences.</p>
            <p>To which it may be anſwered, that thoſe Conſciences ſhould be firſt examined, and then Rectified, rather then ſuch an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall alteration ſhould be made of that Sacred and ſetled Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of the Church; And again it is contrary to Reaſon, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48137:9"/>the Rules of Government to Repeal, or to overthrow a Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, Generall and well ſetled Law, becauſe a few either Sickbraind, or Diſſembling ſort of People do quarrell at it: Firſt let ſuch men be well examined, whether it be Conſcience or Covetouſneſs, that is moſt predominant with them. And that you may eaſily diſcover by this Touchſtone, <hi>viz.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be willing to ſet forth as much Land for the Miniſter, as is equivalent to the value of his Tithes, if he will ſo do, then am I ſo charitable as to think, that perſons Conſcience to be truly tender, and great pitty it were to offend it. But this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Caſe may better be compoſed by a Temporary, or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall agreement betwixt the Parſon and ſuch Pariſhioner, then by altering of a generall Law, for the ſatisfaction of ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, whoſe number you will find very inconſiderable to the multitude, &amp; happily his Poſterity, or he that ſhal ſucceed him in his dwelling, may be of another mind; And then as good cauſe to alter the Law again. And thus by ſeeking to pleaſe the Humors of ſome particular perſons, a Fundamentall of the Law muſt be infringed, not only to the Generall prejudice of the Mininſters, but alſo to the Publick incertainty, and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the propriety of all men.</p>
            <p>But if by this Eſſay, you find ſuch tender conſcience, neither willing to pay Tithe, nor any thing elſe in Lieu thereof to the Miniſter; you may conclude him either Covetous, Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or Schiſmatical; For whoſe ſake it is to be hoped that thoſe in Supreme Power will not hold it fit to make ſuch a general alteration in ſo Sacred a Revenue, but rather that ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſcrupulous perſons be brought to conformity to the good old Law of the Land, then to make the Lawes of Church and Commonwealth conformable unto them. Thoſe whom Providence lately prevented, from deſtroyin both Miniſtry, Church Maintenance and Propriety, will yet be glad to ſee ſuch an univerſall Alteration, as a ſtep leading to their deſign.</p>
            <p>Let us yet examin this ſcrupled Conſcience a little further, and ſee if any thing there be in ſacred Scripture to raiſe this ſcruple; for it muſt ariſe, either from the originall inſtitution of them, or from the end whereunto they were inſtituted. Their originall inſtitution is either by the Divine Morall Law, and Law of Nature; or by the Judiciall and Nationall Law of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48137:10"/>Jewes; Or by the Leviticall Law; Or by the Ceremoniall Law. For theſe four (if we may make ſo many of them) are all the opinions we read of, that have been broached of the <hi>Quo Jure</hi> of Tithes.</p>
            <p>Now if they be due by the Divine Morrall Law, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law of Nature, that bindes all People, in all Places, and at all times, and from thence there can ariſe no Scruple.</p>
            <p>If in the next place it be granted, that they are Judicialls, and ſo obligatory to the Jewes as their Nationall Law; Then by that reaſon it muſt follow, that Tithes ought to be paid in this Nation, becauſe they are due to the Miniſters, by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Law of this Land, which ought to be as binding here in <hi>England,</hi> as it was amongſt the Jewes, from whom <hi>England</hi> had its Pattern and example, which is the moſt that can be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid of a Jewiſh continuance with us; yet not that we are in Love with it, becauſe it was Jewiſh, but like it, becauſe it was the Lords ordinance Judiciall, if not Morall.</p>
            <p>If Leviticall. Hence indeed may ariſe a Scruple, becauſe the Leviticall Law is ended in our Saviour. But that they are not of Leviticall Inſtitution, ſome give this anſwer (that would prove them due by the Law of Nature) that Tithes were paid before the Leviticall Law given, by <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and therefore cannot be Leviticall. Others anſwer, that all that is Leviticall in Tithes is only their Aſſignation to the Levites for their ſervice, and that ſervice being ended, the Right of Tithes return again to the Lord, the Donor, by him to be diſpoſed of according to his good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>If Ceremoniall; Then true it is that Tithes are not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, amongſt Chriſtians, foraſmuch as it is agreed, that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicialia ſunt Mortua,</hi> and may be imitated, and taken up in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample again: But <hi>Ceremonialia ſunt mortifera,</hi> deadly and not to be revived or continued; But the double anſwer laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned to the Leviticall anſwereth the Ceremoniall pretence alſo, but becauſe a threefold Cord is not eaſily broken, take hereunto this third anſwer alſo, that they were not Ceremoniall, foraſmuch as they did neither ſignifie, nor Typifie any thing.</p>
            <p>But the end of Tithes is the Honour and ſervice of God, (which no conſcience may ſcruple at) and maintenance not of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48137:10"/>the Levites only, but of the Miniſters of the Goſpell of Chriſt at all times to remain, ſo long as the Miniſtry ſhall ſtand, and though not paid in the Apoſtles time, or times of perſecution, yet were they by the Ancient Fathers ſucceeding, the Apoſtles challenged to the Church as the Lords Ordinance for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Miniſtry, and by univerſall conſent of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome firſt or laſt paid. For as ſoon as the ſtate of the Church could permit and admit thereof, Chriſtians held it moſt Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Fit, that God ſhould as before the Law, and under the Law, have his ancient Revenue of Tithes after the Law.</p>
            <p>Wherein I would not be miſtaken,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>S.</hi> Epiſt. p. 8.11. and cap. 8. p. 243.244.</note> as if I did affirm that the Tenth part (when I ſpeak of the payment of Tithes) was ſo univerſally paid, but that ſome part more or leſſe of the Fruits of the Earth in kind were paid. For you may ſee that <hi>Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> or <hi>Decimatio</hi> do not alwayes ſignifie either a reall Tithe, or a Tenth part, but ſometimes money paid in Lieu of Tithe, or as it were of the nature of Tithe, ſo called, but not ſo in truth in the ſtatutes of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8.21. and 37. <hi>H.</hi> 8.12.<note place="margin">Sir <hi>H. Sp.</hi> c: 14. p. 67:</note> and the Decree made upon them concerning <hi>London.</hi> And ſometimes leſſe then a Tenth, as the four Thraves of Corn, of every Plow-Land, in the Eaſt Riding of <hi>York,</hi> given by King <hi>Athelſton</hi> to the Church of <hi>Beverly,</hi> which came not neer to a Tenth, is ſtiled <hi>Decimae</hi> in the Bull of the Pope. And the gift of two Sheaves in an ancient <hi>Chartulary</hi> there remembred, is called <hi>Decimatio.</hi> And for ſatisfaction herein, you may ſee the Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologie of the word <hi>Decima</hi> or Tithe, to ſignifie the Tenth, whether it be the Tenth part or not. But this by way of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, which yet may ſerve to reconcile many diſputes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Quota,</hi> or part ththed, if well and rightly weighed.</p>
            <p>But to return once more to the Scrupulous Conſcience, for I am loath to leave him unſatisfied, or at leaſt unconvinced. It is the Generall tenet of all the Learned, that Tithes are neither Ceremoniall, nor Leviticall, otherwiſe then in their Aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Levites for the Service of the Tabernalce. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> well knew, that the Leviticall and Ceremoniall Law were ended, and would never have uſed an Antiquated Law for Argument, or proof of the Right of the Miniſters of the Goſpell, as he doth that of <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.4. <hi>Of Muzling the Ox, &amp;c.</hi> If that Law had not been rather Naturall then Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48137:11"/>moniall. But though that ſervice be ended of the Levites, yet the end whereat that maintenance aimed, was the ſervice of God, which the Miniſters of the Goſpell yet performing, That very maintenance <hi>ex Congruo,</hi> and by Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> aforeſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument (if not from the Divine morall Law, yet) from the Politicall Law of the Jewes not wholly cancelled, belongs to the Miniſters of the Goſpell, which none but the moſt ſeditious Sect of Anabaptiſts will deny, who denying alſo the very Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry it ſelf, can do no leſſe then deny their maintenance, to whom I ſhall give no other Anſwer then before, as to the Right of Tithes. And for their other opinions concerning the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry it ſelf, they have been abundantly confuted, by many of the Learned, and it is a proper Subject for the Divine to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, if any thing <hi>De Novo</hi> can be allegded by them.</p>
            <p>But here I truſt is ſufficient matter ſhewed to prove Tithes to be due, either by the Divine Morall, or Naturall Law, or by the Poſitive Law of this Nation, wherein the Canoniſts, and Divines generally holding the Divine Morall Right, the Schoolemen, Papiſts, and many others the Poſitive Lawes of each Nation, which queſtion, I will not take upon me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, foraſmuch as Tithes being the Miniſters due here in <hi>England,</hi> by either of thoſe wayes; it ſerves the turn for this diſcourſe, the Scope and aime thereof only being, to ſatisfie the Reader, that whether Tithes are due here, by the one Law, or the other to the Church, that they may not be taken from it, nor a ſtipend, or other thing to be exchanged for them, without the conſent of Parſon, and Patron at leaſt.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe, that could that Divine Morall Right to the Tenth part be ſufficiently eleered, that this would eaſily reſolve the reſt; and no man could then go about the Alteration here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but he muſt ſet God himſelf at defiance: But ſo much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being herein proved, as that by the Divine Morall Law, an Honourable Portion in kind, is due to the Miniſter of the Goſpell, and many Ancient and modern writers have held, and do maintain the ſetled maintenance belonging to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be the Portion of Divine Right belonging to it, That which I ſhall now ſay, is by way of Caveat to them in Supreame power, that it highly concerns them (if they intend any alteration herein) to be ſully ſatisfied in this Point of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48137:11"/>Right, as well for the kinde, as for the <hi>quota,</hi> before they go about it; for it is not for men of dubious thoughts, but well reſolved, by ſound and ſolid Arguments, to undertake a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this ſacred Revenue, for if either the kinde or <hi>quota</hi> be Moral, the Alteration is deſperate; and why ſhould Supreme Power run the hazard of a curſe from Heaven upon themſelves, and the whole Nation, by reſolving that which at leaſt is que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, not with men only, but between them and God, to whom the judgement belongs; There, to be given, where he is the only Advocate, whoſe Spouſe (if the Right be hers) is diſinherited. Religion and Policy both, prompt men in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters dubious to reſolve of the ſafeſt courſe; No danger in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the Miniſter maintenance as it ſtands eſtabliſhed, but great hazard in the commuting.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Argument for this Exchange, is, that the way of Tithing is a contentious way of maintenance of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and for peace ſake ſome other way muſt be found out for their ſubſiſtence, leſſe ſubject to contention.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who frame this for a reaſon of the Alteration, ſcarce look ſo far as to the Donor of this ſacred maintenance; for if they did, then would they conſider that God himſelf made this a Law among the <hi>Jews</hi> his own ſelect people; (to goe no higher, having ſaid enough thereof before) And unleſſe wee will be wiſer then he who is Wiſdome it ſelf, wee may not cenſure this way of maintenance for contentious, nor hold forth any other as more peaceable for <hi>Jews</hi> or Chriſtians, the Chriſtians imitating them who did receive their Law from the mouth of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>Certainly had there been a more peaceable way to have been found out, for maintenance of Gods Miniſters, the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcient and Omnipotent Lord, as he muſt needs have known it, ſo his Goodneſſe and Power is ſuch, that he would have ſo appointed it; Let us then lay our hands upon our mouthes, and be filent, or if we will be ſpeaking, let us condemn out own fooliſhneſſe, and magnifie his wiſdome.</p>
            <p>But becauſe it is the corrupt nature of man to be finding out inventions, and to be always changing, though for the worſe, before we fall upon this Exchange, with us, let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whether the <hi>Jews</hi> did, or lawfully might have been
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48137:12"/>ſuch Exchangers? that they had cauſe ſo to be, (if conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be a cauſe) is evident, for there wanted not amongſt them who withheld, ſubtracted, and witbdrew their Tithes, as now amongſt us, witneſſe the complaint of the Prophet, and the vain-glorious boaſting of the Phariſee, that <hi>He paid Tithe of all that he poſſeſſed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.8. Luke 18.12.</note> implying that others did not; that their natural inclinations prompted them to it, is apparent; for they were and yet are the greateſt Brokers and Exchangers that the world affords. THat they yet did not put ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change in practice, it is evident by that of our Saviour in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Luke 11.42.</note> 
               <hi>Yee Tithe Mint, and Rue, &amp;c.:</hi> and that of the pround Phariſee before; ſo that you ſee, that though the <hi>Jewes</hi> were the moſt perverſe and ſtiff-necked people of all others, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they were the only ſelect Nation) yet they were not grown to this height of impiety, as to exchange the ſacred Patrimony by a Law.</p>
            <p>Let us then examine the ſecond part, Whether lawfully they might have been ſuch Exchangers of Tithes? Obſerve here, that I do intend the firſt Tenth paid to the <hi>Levites,</hi> not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Tenth out of the nine parts, which the two firſt yeares were to be brought to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there to be ſpent in Feaſts, and the third year upon the poor and <hi>Levites</hi> within his own gates: For if the way were too far from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then by <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.31. they might change thoſe Tithes into money, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a fifth part more to them, (which few of our Exchangers will be willing to doe.) But the Inquiſition here handled is of the firſt tenth, Whether the <hi>Jewes</hi> might lawfully have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed that? which I am perſwaded, no man of ſound judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will maintain: For the allowance of their exchange of the ſecond tenth in caſe <hi>Supra,</hi> excludes the exchange of the other. Now what was it that might hinder this exchange, we will ſpare the Divine Right, for wee have ſpoken enough of that before; But admitting that did not impede, then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it muſt be the Judicial Law given them that did reſtrain them from it. If ſo, then why ſhould not our Humane Poſitive Laws withhold us from the like? If you will make the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to reſt in this, that God more immediatly preſcribed that to the <hi>Jewes</hi> for their National Law, then this Poſitive Law to us; this is a difference without a diverſity, for by that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48137:12"/>reaſon the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſhould have been more ſtrictly bound to the obſervation of the Decalogue, (though Moral) then Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. And again, it was a Law given to them for their Nation, not excluſive, that no other Nation ſhould uſe it, but rather as a pattern for other Nations to imitate; and ſo it being unto the <hi>Jews</hi> but a bare Judiciall Law, it could be no more bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them by reaſon of a more immediate preſcription, then to us by a mediate imitation, having not ſo much the <hi>Jewes</hi> for example, as God for the Authour of that Law.</p>
            <p>Again, whence ariſeth the ground of this contention, which makes the Miniſters maintenance by Tithing ſo litigious, as that ſome new way for their ſubſiſtence muſt be found out? Doth this contention ariſe from the Parſons part, or from the Pariſhoner? If on the Pariſhioners part, then in Juſtice and Reaſon, ought Supreme Power to provide better Laws to compel the Pariſhioner to pay his due, and not to enforce the Parſon to depart with his indiſputable Right, becauſe his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioner doth him wrong, for that were all one, as if my neighbour have a mind to my houſe, or land, and becauſe I will not let him have it, he will diſſeiſe or diſpoſſiſſe me of it, and then Supreme Power to make a Law to enforce me to take money or another thing for it; whereas Authority is ordained by God, <hi>to puniſh him that doth wrong, and to relieve the innocent and him that is injur'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that the Pariſhioner is the contentious perſon in this caſe,<note place="margin">The Judges of Aſſiſe are able to teſtifie this Truth.</note> it is manifeſt by the multitude of actins that the people put the Parſons to, wherein the Tryals generally and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go with the Parſon who is injured, and from whom right is detained; whereunto the people are the more encouraged, becauſe Tithes have been diſcountenanced, the ancient reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for their recovery partly taken away, the Title ſcandalized, as if the payment of them were ſuperſtitious, and Popiſh, and againſt the Laws both of GOd and man, which the people moſt greedily ſwallow, and no ſatisfaction endeavoured to be given to the avaritious multitude of their Legality: But as if the payment of them were as bad as clamor makes them, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hopes are daily fed and heightned by holding forth of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proviſions intended for them; whereas in point of Juſtice, Governors ſhould make new Laws to ſuppreſſe new deceitful
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48137:13"/>Inventions, and confirm all Legal Intereſts and Proprieties.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee how it comes to paſſe that payment of Tithes is looked upon as contentious and troubleſome, becauſe the people make it firſt litigious, and then cry out for an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment, or change at leaſt, becauſe it is litigious; as if it were lawful for one to take away the goods of another, and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for him whoſe goods they were to uſe his lawful remedy for their recovery: Or, (yet more plainly) as if it were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſteal, and then to hang him up whoſe goods were ſtoln, for proſecuting the Thief: If this be not, I know not what is, the calling <hi>evil good, and good evil, the juſtifying of the wicked, and condemning the juſt,</hi> the reward whereof you may ſee in one word,<note place="margin">Eſa. 5.20.23. Prov. 17.15.</note> 
               <hi>Wo, Eſa.</hi> 5.20.23. which general word compriſeth all particular judgements here and hereafter, temporal and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal.</p>
            <p>Nor is the payment of Tithes contentious, becauſe the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſues for more then his Right, but becauſe the Pariſhioner will not pay what he ought: and the proof of the values reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as well of the one ſide as the other, the Pariſhioner is too hard for the Parſon frequently, which gives an inlet, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a wide gap both to Witneſſes and to Jury men, (who never were friends to Tithes) of the greateſt and moſt familiar per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, that happeneth in any Tryals whatſoever; And all with impunity, for want of ſome Superior Court, whereunto the Judges of Aſſiſe may binde ſuch Jurors to appears and to anſwer for their miſdemeanors in thoſe trials. And that by the Law as now it ſtands, the Plaintiffe can recover no coſts of Suit: In which two caſes, if Authority would provide remedy, Tithes would be paid with leſſe ſcruple and contention by far, then now they are, and leſſe difficult would it be for them in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power to provide Laws for the more juſt payment of Tithes, and avoiding Suits and Contentions therein, then to find out and eſtabliſh a new Proviſion in lieu of them, which at the beſt will tacitely cenſure the Wiſdome of God, as hath been ſhewed; For this contention ariſeth not from the nature or manner of Tithes, but from thoſe who rob God and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of them.</p>
            <p>And again, ſuch new Proviſion muſt neceſſarily ariſe either out of the Land, ſubject to the payment of Tithes, or elſe out of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48137:13"/>the publick Treaſury. If not of the Land, I demand then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee that now ſcruples at, or contends in the payment of Tithes, will not be as troubleſome and contentious in payment of another thing in lieu of them? It is not to be doubted, but he will, if the conteſt ariſe from the thing it ſelf, which is the ſcruple and conteſt of the Anabaptiſt and Sectary, who diſrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Miniſtery it ſelf; and therefore ſcruple and contend at any maintenace at all, and they fall not under this diſpute of Alteration, who are altogether for abolition.</p>
            <p>But if the conteſt ariſe about the name of Tithes or other ground, then poſſibly they may not be ſcrupulous or contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to allow another thing, which as is ſhewed before, may more eaſily be compoſed by a private agreement, then by a publick and general Act; for difficult will it be, by a general Act, to make the exchange equal, or at leaſt ſuch as the Church may not be a loſer, and yet the Pariſhioner not think himſelf o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharged; which if he be, or do but think himſelf ſo to be, how contentious will he prove? and how litigious will be the payment? and ſo in ſtead of one evil ſpirit conjured down, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will be raiſed up.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe the Pariſhioner be made to pay his Tithes to the State, and the Miniſter to have his pay from the publick Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, (which is the moſt likely project.) How intricate a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will it be found to ſettle a due Stipend? Some Pariſhes are greater then other; ſome Miniſters more deſerving then other; ſome having a greater charge of wife and children then other; ſome in birth and education brought up at an higher charge then other; ſome places dearer to live in then other: All which, with a multitude of other difficulties, are to be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſideration, and then if the Stipend be not fixed to the place, every removal and ſucceſſion will require a new Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in perpetuity.</p>
            <p>If the Miniſter of each Pariſh be to receive out of the publick Treaſury the rent of the Tithes of his Pariſh; Firſt, beſides that, that the Pariſhioners will not be pleaſed to pay their Tithes to the State-Officer, Tenant, or Collector, the Parſon cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his due, for the Tenant, Officer, or Collector are to have their ſhare out of it, then the Treaſurer, Auditor, Tellers, Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, and many other publick Officers, and their Clerks and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48137:14"/>Attendants, are to have their ſalaries, and the State muſt not be a loſer; and by that time that all theſe have had their ſhares out of a fat Benefice, how lean will the Parſon look? though there were no bribery to be thought on, for Publicans will not be always Saints, nor will Saints be always Publicans. And how naked ſhall the poor Parſon be, when he hath neither hay, ſtraw. nor food for horſe or beaſt, nor bread, drink, or meat for himſelf or family, nor one pound of wooll to clothe them all? Thoſe that live in Cities, or in Market Towns, (if they have money) may provide ſuch neceſſaries; but how will it fare with thoſe who live in Countrey Villages, eſpecially remote from Markets? So that upon the matter there muſt be for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place a peculiar Alteration, and for every Alteration a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Law. Thoſe that ſeek peace in an unjuſt way, let them in ſo ſeeking aſſure themſelves that they ſhall finde contention and trouble enough: For <hi>Opus Juſtitiae eſt Pax.</hi> Peace is the fruit or effect of Juſtice, not of Injuſtice, for which you may ſee the ſacred Text, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 32.17. <hi>Dum Pacem habemus Bellum quaerimus,</hi> they who deſtroy Religion with one hand, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice with t'other, who hold <hi>Meum</hi> in th'one hand, and <hi>Tuum</hi> in t'other, who will keep what they have, and get what they can, by deſtroying Religion, Law, and Propriety, let their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme be, <hi>Sic quaerimus Bellum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third Argument there is, That this way of Tithing is an incertain way of maintenance for the Miniſter, and therefore ſome new way to be found out that ſhall be more certain.</p>
            <p>This reaſon ſounds as if Miniſters were weary of the old ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Revenue, and now ſought for an Alteration: But herein certainly the Miniſter is injured, it is not their ſeeking, nor can they in conſcience or prudence deſire any exchange. Firſt, with what conſcience can they ſeek it, or accept of it, when that they and all the Learned know and acknowledge the way of Tithing to be a Moral Inſtitution, and an Evangelical Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the Miniſters maintenance, and nothing but the <hi>quota</hi> or part controverted in it. And if by an Alteration the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous conſcience of one Lay man be quieted, the conſciences of all the Clergy will hereby be offended.</p>
            <p>Nor can the Clergy in prudence deſire it, if they do but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how their right and title to their Tithes is honoured by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48137:14"/>Venerable Antiquity, and eſtabliſhed, ratified and confirmed by all the Poſitive Laws of this Nation; and that the wits of all Ages ſince it became Chriſtian, could invent or excogitate. And how long will it be before Stipends will gain that Repute, or be ratified by like Authority? And if Right, backed with ſuch Authority, and Antiquity, cannot now ſupport Tithes, with how ſmall a blaſt will Stipends of a new ſtamp be blown away?</p>
            <p>Again, let us examine wherein the incertainty of Tithes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, that requireth ſuch Exchange. Is Tithe more incertain then the nine parts? Can the Husbandman promiſe to himſelf a more certain encreaſe in his Nine parts, then the Parſon can do of his Tenth? Or, doth not the Tithe yield as certain a Rent or Revenue, as the nine parts? And doth not the Parſon pay as certain a Monethly taxe for his Tenth part, as the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman for his Nine? And what incertainty is there more in the telling of ten Cocks of Corn, then in the telling of ten pounds of money? There is thus much more certainty in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Tithe, then of a Stipend, that the Tithe hath been certainly paid in Harveſt, and a Stipend will be certainly paid when the Parſon can get it. So you ſee Nature pays its due certainly, man incertainly, and yet the incertainty of man cryed up to be certain, and the immutability of Nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for incertainty.</p>
            <p>By what then hath been ſaid, you may diſcover the invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of thoſe motives of ſcrupulous conſciences, contentions, and incertainties held forth as grounds and cauſes for the Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this Sacred Revenue. All other Arguments for this Alteration are more clamorous then colourable. Theſe I take to be the moſt ſober, and yet not ſolid pretences, but ſuch as beſt deſerved a ſatisfactory Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Now whether in Juſtice ſuch a Mutation may be, or not, by Supreme Power profeſſing to govern by the known Laws of the Land, is conſiderable, and I truſt that without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, may by the Rules of Juſtice and Reaſon, admit of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition: For this is not to limit their Power,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coke lib.</hi> 4.13. <hi>&amp;c. lib.</hi> 8. in caſe of the Colledge of Phyſitians.</note> but to rectifie Judgement.</p>
            <p>It is a Maxime in the Law, that an Act of Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Commmon Right and Reaſon, or againſt the Law of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48137:15"/>God, is <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> null and void. If a Law therefore ſhould be made to deſtroy an innocent perſon, either in his life or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, this would be <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> void; or if to take away the Right of another againſt his will, without a crime, it would be null and void: Much more Illegal will it be to deſtroy or take away the Right of a Society, Function, or Profeſſion of men. And becauſe ſome Miniſters have been contentious, that therefore all muſt ſuffer. The Schoolmen hold it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to excommunicate a Corporation, or Society, out of a preſumption that ſome of them may be Innocent.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall urge preſidents either Forain, or Domeſtick, Former, or Recent, here with us; it is anſwered, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, that preſidents are not always to be practiſed, nor is the commonneſſe of an offence any States juſtification; You may know, that neither Monaſteries, &amp;c. veſted in the Crown or State, till the Corporation, Order, &amp;c. were diſſolved. But now the Miniſters Right is to be taken away, and yet the Miniſtery to ſtand: and if it be not lawful to take away their Right, the conferring of another thing upon them in exchange, will not cure the wrong. <hi>Ahab</hi> was not grown to that height of—as to act ſuch Impiety.</p>
            <p>Authority is ordained by God and man, to juſtifie the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and puniſh the Guilty, to maintain right and ſuppreſs wrong. Are not therefore ſome fiery ſpirits condemned, and that juſtly, that of late voted down Right, I mean the Right of Patronages? Doth it not concern others then to bee very wary, how they go about to turn Tithes into Stipends, or ſome other thing, whereby they doe not onely take away the Parſons Right, but the Patrons too, and in the alteration of the one, they deſtroy the other.<note place="margin">2 <hi>part. Inſt. p.</hi> 646.661.364.</note> For you may read in a Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Writer of the Law, that if you take away the Tithe from the Parſon, you take away the Right of Patronage from the Patron; for in a Writ of Right of Advowſon, (which is one of the moſt ancient Writs of the Law) the Patron muſt make his Title to the Patronage, by alledging the taking of the Tithes by the Parſon; for the whole benefit of the Patron conſiſteth in conferring his Tithes upon his Chaplain; and if the Tithes be taken from him, the Advowſon or Right of Patronage doth vaniſh as a thing without fruit or benefit. Other Writs and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48137:15"/>matters of Antiquity might be produced for the Rights of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronages, which we truſt to be needleſs now to urge, ſince the vote for taking away thoſe Rights of the People, hath been condemned by all ſober men, as a thing ſo deſtructive to Right and Propriety, that no man could have told where ſuch High Injuſtice would have ended. Let them then that now or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall fit in the Seat of Authority be well adviſed, how by the Alteration of one Fundamentall point of the Law, or of the Propriety of one ſort, Condition or Quality of perſons, they do not deſtroy another; and by the opening of ſuch a Gap, make way to the Ruine and deſtruction of all.</p>
            <p>May we not now rather bewaile the mean, poor, deſpicable and contemptible condition of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſhe is at this day Reduced; Then to ſeek to take from her, that one, Onely and Single Right of Tithes, that is left her: Her Rights, Liberties, and Priviledges were ſo Numerous hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that no former Age held it ſafe to begin their enumerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to ſum them up, leſt any ſhould be omitted. Nor did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Act of Parliament hitherto enumerate them; though the great Charter of this Nation did particulariſe, and ſpecifie the Rights and Liberties of the Lay People,<note place="margin">2. Part Inſt. p. 3.4.</note> and no other are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed unto them, but what were therein mentioned, yet the Rights, Priviledges, and Liberties of Holy Church not being held ſafe to be then numbred, are by that <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Church, confirmed in termes of Generality, and that Form only of Confirmation uſed by all Succeeding Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Of all the Ornaments that did ſet forth her Beauty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, whereof ſhe is now deflowred, ſhall we not leave her one Jewell or Enſigne, wherby ſhe may be known, you that are now her Enemies, and ſolicite Supreme Power ſtill againſt her, be now charitable at laſt, afflict not her that mourneth. neither adde ſorrow to her affliction. Think upon the Curſes of them who perſecute ſuch as the Lord hath ſmitten,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. and <hi>Eſay</hi> the 47. throughout.</note> and talk how they may vex them, whom the Lord hath wounded.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who bear the Sword, have been highly ſucceſſeful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt men in their Millitary imployment, and let them not take this Caveat in evill part, to be way of contending with God, for they that ſhall alter this Sacral Revenue of the Chucrh muſt take upon them to reſolve the Point of Divinity, which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48137:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>all the Learned of former Ages throughout all Chriſtendome have left undermined; and yet moſt of them both Ancient and Modern, have held with the Divine Right, which if it ſhould now be Reſolved amiſs, how can you afterwards expect that the Heavens ſhould favour you. And again what an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake may we imagine will ariſe amongſt Proprieties, if this lead the Dance? And if ſuch a Judgement begin at the Houſe of God, and in the Sacred Revenue, what may we think will be the iſſue of Common and Lay-Proprieties?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if Divine Right will not ſupport this Church-Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, yet me thinkes Humane Right may be ſufficient to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. For the Lawes for Eccleſiaſticall Rights are as Poſitive, and ought to be as powerfull, as for Temporall Rights; therefore is ſaid,<note place="margin">2. Part Inſt. p. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Quod Jura Eccleſiae, publicis aequiparantur,</hi> and that it which is Granted to the Church for the Honour of God, and maintenance of his Religion and ſervice (as men muſt acknowledge tithes were) is Granted for and to God. And if ſo, not in the Power of man, to take away from his Miniſters againſt their wills, wherein I would not be miſtaken, as if I did limit Supreme Power, or derogate from it; But my meaning is to aſcribe that Honour to it, which the Law requires that all men ſhould have of it, that is, that they cannot, becauſe they will not, do an unjuſt thing, wherein the Gods on Earth do reſemble the God of Heaven. For if when it is ſaid that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power may do what they will, this ſhal be extended that whatſoever they will do, be it juſt or unjuſt, is lawfull; that is an apparent error. For never was any ſuch Power given unto men, as that their wils ſhould be a Law: For this is the Peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Prerogative of the great God For what he wils is alwayes; juſt, becauſe he wills it; But what man wills is never good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be juſt.</p>
            <p>We read but of one amongſt the Heathen that could ſay, <hi>Sic volo, ſic Jubeo, ſtet pro Ratione voluntas.</hi> And but of one other in ſacred ſtory, of whom it was ſaid, thus it muſt be, and thus it muſt not be, for <hi>Hophni</hi> will not have it thus, but ſo, it is God only who is eſſentially juſt, Man is juſt, but accidentally as he is well, or ill affected and therefore a Subject improper to whom ſuch an abſolute power ſhould be allowed, as that his will ſhould be a Law. Nor do we read that ever any ſetled Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48137:16"/>or Governors claimed a Power <hi>de Jure</hi> to deprive an Innocent man, or a Profeſſion, or Society of Innocent men of their Rights, which by the Lawes of that Land are, and ſtand veſted and ſetled in them. For what were this, but a meer Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government, to ſay no worſe of it, we treat not of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Nations, becauſe (we think) we are a ſetled Government. And yet <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror loſt nothing by confirming the Rights of the Church in the firſt place,<note place="margin">Ann<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 4to in his Survey of All the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Lawes of the Land.</note> and Tithes thereunto in particular, for though not his Line, yet his Regiment continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till theſe dayes. And it ſeldome goes well long with the Commonwealth, when it goes ill with the Church.</p>
            <p>Thus have I endeavoured in this diſcourſe (though with too much weakneſs for ſo Pious a Patrimony, yet with ardent zeal) to preſer the Church from ſuffering and diſſwade others from tranſgreſſing, in altering this Sacred Revenue into a ſtipend, or other thing. By ſhewing the Primary owner to be Lord in a Peculiar manner. The Lord to be the firſt Donor to his firſt Prieſt before the Law; To the Levites <hi>pro Tempore</hi> under the Law. And afterwards to the Evangelicall Miniſtry in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity. Who may neither <hi>per Factum, nec per Feoffamentum nec pro Excambium</hi> alienate or alter them to the Churches pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice; Nor to be either Agents, or willingly Patients in this permutation. Foraſmuch as this Revenue in its kinde is moſt Naturall, moſt convenient, moſt equall. The Inſtitution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the thing (if not in the <hi>Quota</hi> alſo) by the Divine Morall or Naturall Law. The Donation or Aſſignation both of the Thing and of the <hi>Quota</hi> or Part, Judiciall to the Jewes, Not Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, nor the Thing Leviticall, otherwiſe then in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation <hi>pro Tempore;</hi> Since the Law, the Thing it ſelf at leaſt in kinde (if not in the <hi>Quota</hi> alſo) Evangelicall. The Thing and <hi>Quota</hi> by the Judiciall, Nationall &amp; Poſitive Lawes of <hi>England</hi> eſtabliſhed, veſted, and ſetled in the Church as her Propriety, Not in the Legiſlative Power (for ſo much as concerneth the Divine Morall or Naturall Right thereof) to be altered: Nor (without offence be it ſpoken) for what thereof concerneth the Judiciall or Poſitive Lawes of this Nation, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parſon and Patron, to be changed; Neither upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Scruple, Contention, Incertainty, or Inequality, nor any other pretence whatſoever. For <hi>Juſtitia eſt Suum Cuique
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48137:17"/>tribuere, (Suum non Alienum)</hi> that is to ſay, Juſtice gives to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his own, Not to one man that which is anothers; So that no Reſpect whatſoever ought to incline a Judge to give Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Law or Right.</p>
            <p>In all or any of which particulars wherein I have fallen ſhort (For it was not my purpoſe to be tedious, nor to Muſter up the Objections, or Anſwers for, or againſt the Riſe the Author, the Right or the <hi>Quota</hi> of Tithes, which are enough to be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of a voluminous Book, but only to ſhew the Dogmaticall truths, and the Conceſſions, if not of all, yet of the Generality of Writers in this Summary diſcourſe) I truſt ſome others more able will afford their helping hand for the ſupport of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Revenue, which is the laſt of the flowers of the Churches Temporall Garland now left her, that is conſiderable. And it is to be hoped, (if it be well defended now by able <hi>Pens</hi>) that it will be the laſt Conflict and Conteſt ſhe ſhall find againſt this Judiciall at Leaſt, Divine Patrimony, which hath this only Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary to confute or ſatisfie now remaining, eſpecially if the Eyes of the people were but once open, and their underſtanding enlightned, and their hopes of Gain (their great <hi>Diana</hi>) abated, by looking upon <hi>Holland</hi> our Siſter Commonwealth, <hi>France</hi> and other Places where Tithes have been tranſlated only from the Miniſters, to the State Commiſſioners, where they, and I will both end in this Alteration, For <hi>Quod Non capit Chriſtus, capit Fiſcus,</hi> what is not paid to the Church, muſt be paid to the <hi>Checquer. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde Nulla Redemptio,</hi> from whence there is No Return.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48137:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
